Underscoring the global nature private
credit in the credit cycle, one of
India's largest junk borrowers just
decided it's going to delay the cash
interest and principal payments on one
of India's biggest junk bonds. But who
is it that owns these junk bonds? Well,
some of the biggest names in private
credit like Cerberus and some of the
biggest global banks like Deutsche Bank.
Now, this bond is not going to bring
down either of those. In fact, that's
not what we're really looking for here.
Not a failure of Deutsche Bank becoming
the next Lehman. Instead, what we're
looking for more importantly, signs of
the credit cycle as well as the downside
consequences from it, the dreaded credit
crunch. That's what we're really after
here. Now, to this day, 18 years after
Bear Stearns and Lehman Brothers,
everyone keeps looking for the next one.
That's not what we're really talking
about here with private credit, the
bubble now the bust. Banks themselves
are not going to go belly up like they
did during that fateful year of 2008.
It's not that we would expect a bank to
fail because of private credit, nor one
of the household shadow bank names like
BlackRock or Blackstone. But a smaller
shadow bank, that's well within the
realm of possibilities. And the question
you need to ask is, what would that do
to the entire monetary and financial
ecosystem? So, we're already seeing
again signs of concerns that showing up
places like repo, where expectations are
rising that repo rates might see a
significant spike by summertime. And
that's already in addition to Treasury
bills that are being
valued quite richly compared to
investment considerations alone. I'll go
over both of those mean and what the
what's really going on right now. But
even if leverage private credit does
progress into stage three, and we're at
stage two right now, and there does get
to be a fair amount of wider monetary
disruption due to it, the focus on
failing banks or even just failing
shadow banks somewhat misses the point.
Those are just signals that big things
are going wrong, and it's what's going
wrong and what that means which ends up
being the vastly more important part of
this.
Now, bankruptcies, they make a huge
splash and that's what everyone
remembers. But even if Deutsche Bank
does not become the next Lehman
Brothers, and there's little chance that
it will, that doesn't mean that the
system itself overall can't lead to some
really big time downside consequences.
And what are those consequences if not
for the next Lehman Brothers? That's
where the term credit crunch comes in.
And more importantly, when a credit
crunch becomes what economists call a
unit root. That's what we're really
after here. Private credit shadow
banking unit root credit crunch. And
I'll explain what all these are.
And what did the most damage in 2008?
Wasn't Lehman Brothers itself. It was
the credit crunch which developed from
the systemic breakdown of which Lehman,
Bear, AIG, Wachovia, all of them, they
were symptoms. They were symptoms.
The permanent pyramid to the banking and
money flow which came afterward, that's
the thing. You don't need a big name
failure to suffer from a crunch, and
that's what the focus needs to be right
now, particularly since this thing is
indeed global. It's not just contained
to the US or Europe. In fact, we're
reminded of that just recently when
India's Shapoorji
just came out with, quote, India's
biggest private credit borrower and
issuer one of its largest ever junk
bonds has just reinforced this point.
Holders of a high yield note issued by a
unit of the infrastructure conglomerate
unanimously agreed to let the company
delay paying principal and interest to
June 30th, people familiar with the
matter said. The notes are held by a
number of global private credit funds
including Cerberus Capital Management,
Värde Partners, Davidson Kempner, and of
course regulated bank Deutsche Bank, the
one that's most heavily exposed to
private credit around the world. Now,
group representatives, this is back to
the Indian firm, told some investors
earlier this month that the company was
considering a potential offering about
2.6 billion dollar equivalent of dollar
and rupee denominated bonds, according
to people familiar with that matter.
They also said that the proceeds would
be used to refinance the Goswami debt
that just got extended. And oh boy, not
only does this anecdote remind us of the
global nature of a credit cycle, it also
serves as another milestone in that same
downturn. This is one of the clearest
signs of the reverse slope to the cycle
Ponzi scheme borrowing. That's when
troubled debtors really start to borrow
money just to pay back the old
investors. It's an obvious sign of
distress, particularly if or when it
ends up being some of the bigger
borrowers and gets to be more common
among them and to many of their smaller
peers.
You can't keep extending and pretending
if the money starts to dry up. And if
these businesses can't keep convincing
new lenders to lend to them, then the
old lenders begin to pile up losses, or
at the very least they pile up PIK,
which I'll get to, and more selective
defaults. But after enough of those take
place, investors, the entire system
start to get wise to it, which only
feeds into more downside of the cycle.
Risk aversion grows, new money stops
flowing in,
and then you get to the more systemic
parts of the system. Stage two becomes
stage three.
Before we go on with our video today,
let me ask you a question. What if your
gold could actually pay you every single
month in more gold? That's what today's
video sponsor, Monetary Metals, lets you
do.
And here's how it works. You still own
the gold, it's still in your name, it's
fully insured, but instead of just
sitting there doing nothing, it actually
starts working for you. Monetary Metals
has built a system that turns idle gold
into productive gold, earning real yield
paid in physical gold, not dollars. No
selling, no trading, no converting. You
keep your gold, and every month you get
more of it. It's a simple idea, but it
solves a big problem. If gold is money,
it should act like money, and now it
finally can.
If you're a long-term gold holder
looking for a smarter way to store
value, check them out at
monetary-metals.com/snyder.
Again, that's
I highly recommend booking a call with
them today to see if they're the right
fit for you. We thank Monetary Metals
for their sponsorship, and now let's get
back to the rest of our video.
And this is exactly what Deutsche Bank's
Ozan Tarmac was talking about a couple
weeks ago that I highlighted when he
said, "If not for the Iran conflict,
this stuff would be everywhere, all over
the front pages, social media, the
entire thing." This is really important
stuff, but why? That's the point. A lot
of people are saying, "Okay, private
credit, some losses." People argue it's
not a big deal. If it is a big deal,
what does that actually mean?
You're going to have proponents that are
going to downplay the threat at the same
time that critics, and those
increasingly concerned, myself obviously
included, are going to be pointing out
all the flaws. Now, one of those critics
is Jeffrey Gundlach. Not only did he
highlight too much of what he called
garbage lending last fall, the lending
didn't take place last fall, the
highlighting took place last fall.
Earlier this week, Gundlach took aim at
PIK, called payment in kind, which has
gone from a a limited tool to help keep
struggling borrowers in the game and
afloat, to one of the most questionable
tactics that seemingly employed way too
aggressively and too often, thereby the
purpose isn't to help borrowers, it's to
obscure just how much garbage there has
been and what otherwise already been
covered. So, from Gundlach quote, "He
unleashed a storm of criticism this week
seemingly aimed at Red Lobster lender
TCW Group, which where he used to work,
over how the asset manager is valuing
its debt and equity stakes in the
struggling restaurant chain. TCW had
slashed the value of its equity stake in
Red Lobster by roughly 98%
while continuing to value at par roughly
56 million of Red Lobster debt held in a
private business development company or
BDC, which is something Bloomberg
reported earlier. The mark suggests that
TCW is confident that Red Lobster's
overall value remains sufficient to
fully cover the loan, which has grown in
size as interest accrues in kind rather
than being paid out in cash. Now,
private credit proponents will point out
how this is an extreme and isolated
example, but critics like Gunn lack are
going to counter by noting how prevalent
PIK has become and just how opaque
pricing of credit assets has turned the
industry into a full-blown target and
for good reason. The big issues have
always been trust and information and
the two should go hand in hand. Good
information leads to robust trust. As I
said, it's not credit losses that lead
to systemic problems. It's the lack of
trust. But when you start to see too
many examples where the information
instead shows something very different
from previous expectations as I went
over in my last webinar, that's when a
few one-off cockroaches fuel at the
start at least some well-grounded
skepticism. Most people are willing to
give the benefit of the doubt,
especially when they're getting high
returns, but that benefit always comes
with limits and once it starts to get
stretched too far, the only way to
restore functioning markets is for those
in question, the private credit
suppliers, to begin supplying useful
information. Instead, like 2008,
what they've been doing is exactly the
opposite and Blue Owl being the most
prominent example.
And so there's every reason to see how
that's become the case, where stage two
has come from. But what about stage
three? Most people want to know, okay,
stage two progresses to stage three,
what does that mean? Doesn't that mean
something like 2008, another Lehman
Brothers, banks failing all over the
landscape? What is it we're really
talking about here? Now that we see that
there is potentially a downside. We can
argue about how much of a potential that
is, but now that we can see there is
potentially one that we can't dismiss,
what does that actually mean as far as
the real economy, the marketplace, and
anything else in between?
We've been conditioned to think about it
along the lines of bank failures, and
it's understandable why that's been. For
those of us who lived through it, you
remember when they announced Bear
Stearns was not excuse me, merged with
JP Morgan. You know, Lehman Brothers,
AIG, especially those came closely
together. We associate the crisis with
those bankruptcies. But the crisis
wasn't the bankruptcies. They were just
the most obvious symptoms that a crisis
was raging. They didn't cause 2008.
Lehman and Bear were casualties of 2008.
Now, no one remembers which banks
ignited the great collapse in the early
'30s. What is remembered are the
consequences from the systemic
breakdown. And no, I am not saying the
private credit bubble and bust, even in
stage three, is going to lead to another
2008 or the Great Depression. That's not
what we're talking about here. What I am
saying is that what matters is what
happens to the system, not one, two, or
several participants within it. What
turned 2008 and that crisis into the
silent depression was the credit crunch
it unleashed and then made permanent. In
fact, it was that very thing which
ironically birthed the shadow banking
private credit system that we know today
that's gone through the bubble and now
bust cycle. So, banks and now shadow
banks,
they're simply engines to circulate
money throughout the economy and
financial markets, too, for that matter.
A bank failure can impair that engine,
but it can be just as diminished even
when there aren't any more Lehmans. What
matters is not the specific firm, it's
the systemic capacity, which is the main
reason why we always talk here at Euro
Dollar University about balance sheet
capacity. And in a way,
that was just talked about a couple days
ago over at the Bank of England. Quote,
"We shouldn't be in a situation where
this brings down the banking system, but
it might cause a private credit crunch
in the way we had a banking credit
crunch according to the Bank of
England's Sarah Breeden. And what she
said at a conference held by the
Financial Times in London just recently,
too. Breeden doesn't expect a repeat of
the global financial crisis, which was
not financial, it's monetary, but said
regulators are looking for echoes of
that episode as all we as we all should
be. They are concerned that leverage and
lack of disclosure, lack of trust in the
private credit market could lead to a
downturn with that knock-on impact to
the real economy. That's the thing here.
And this is a far bigger deal than it
might seem. Just in our recent
experience, there's a compelling
argument that the private credit bubble
on the way up, the bubble, saved the
United States in particular from going
full-blown recession in 2023,
particularly after the banking crisis.
We got close to it. We stuck with the
forgot-how-to-grow recession type, but
without those shadow banks and the money
that they were providing and re-lending,
it might have been as bad as we saw in
Europe and maybe even worse. So, the
economic consequences from a private
credit crunch, they're already nasty,
and the longer they stick around, the
more damage they do, especially to
employment. That's something else that
Keynes said long ago, another one of the
few things he got right along with the
stock market. Deflation, and a credit
crunch is a manifestation of deflation,
it hits workers the hardest. And that's
just what uh Sarah Breeden was talking
about. It's always the little guy who
ends up bearing the brunt of deflation.
So, a private credit bust, even if there
aren't any huge, newsworthy, major
failures, a bust which leads to a credit
crunch can leave scars all over the
system and especially on the labor
market, which is exactly why the Bank of
England is talking about the possibility
here.
And a lot of those chances really depend
upon systemic liquidity, another angle
on deflation. Circulation of money
through the system so that circulation
of credit can take place and keep the
overall economic system as well as
financial system well-oiled and
well-greased so that everything flow
everything has to move including money
and credit. When they stop moving,
that's where you get to deflation. And
why they stop moving, it can be because
of something like a credit cycle
downturn.
Now, we often hear about the term
liquidity. I mean, you hear it all the
time. What it really means is money
flowing through the system, which is
terribly important at the best of times,
but much more so during trouble. You
want money to flow through credit
because that's how the modern
specialized globalized economy works,
which puts the reserve currency, which
is the eurodollar, not dollar, at the
center of everything. You need the
globalized monetary flow. And money can
flow from one end of the planet to the
other because of it, which is the secret
ingredient in the modern prosperity that
we all enjoyed up until around August
9th of 2007. When that money flow breaks
down, the economy breaks down with the
marketplace in the middle.
Now, the willingness of market
participants, financial participants
overall, to take on risk is paramount,
which is where the private credit story
comes in. They take risk because they
seem reasonable. If the system begins to
believe they are, in fact, unreasonable
due to shadow bankers hiding stress and
PIK or depending way too much on
mark-to-myth, then we do have a growing
problem. It's not the losses, as I said
in the webinar, it's the mistrust. Money
flow dries up, which is what deflation
really means, and when money flow dries
up, then you really get the issues. This
is why we pay so much attention to
things like repo and other kinds of
money flow like FX. It can tell us that
when these problems are rising, lack of
risk-taking that goes along with it,
when they're getting serious, and we
just got another signal along those
lines, going back again to repo. So,
back to Bloomberg here. Traders notched
up record volumes in one narrow corner
of the US interest rate futures market
this week betting on a spread that
reflects potential swings in overnight
lending rates. One side of the trade
involves futures tied to the secured
overnight financing rate or SOFR, a
benchmark rate based on the cost of
borrowing against Treasury securities,
that's repo, while the other references
the effective federal funds rate, the
weighted average of overnight unsecured
rates. So, long story short here, I know
there's a lot of jargon there. The long
story short here, very simple.
What hedgers are hedging against using
what's called a SOFR basis trade is the
possibility that over the next 3 months
SOFR rates will rise back above Fed
funds just like they did quite regularly
last fall. Now, why would repo rates,
which is what SOFR's really made from,
why would repo rates rise like that?
Well, now the mainstream's going to tell
you it's all about the Fed and its bank
reserve. But, all the Fed is going to be
doing going ahead is slowing the pace of
its not QE bill purchases. It's still
going to be buying bills and creating
reserves. Plus, there going to be a lot
more reserves thanks to the government
spending money that it doesn't really
have, which takes them out of its
account, the TGA, it puts them back into
the banking system. But, all that's
irrelevant. Well, when the Fed gives you
only the Fed for everything that
happens, everyone says it must be the
Fed because that's the only way to
explain something in money and banking.
That's all just nonsense. In reality,
it's always risk aversion, dealer
capacity, therefore balance sheet
capacity. Now, why might those become
impaired? Well, one of the potential
fallouts is from the energy shock, which
threatens to trigger the the historical
energy shock case, which would be a
full-blown NBER-style recession,
especially when there wouldn't be a
private credit cushion this time around
to keep it from going all the way.
But, it also might very well be private
credit woes themselves. After all, banks
are already taking steps to lower
collateral valuations to protect
themselves from the shadow banks, which
is not a good sign for willingness to
take risk overall. This stuff is already
taking place. Plus, we already saw repo
last year. And we're also seeing
Treasury bills, as I mentioned in the
intro, priced relatively high again
along with dealers, primary dealers in
this case, hoarding large amounts for
their inventories. They're also hoarding
large amounts of coupons and notes, but
bills, that's another signal you got to
pay attention to. And all of that
pointing to the other side of cash
flowing or not flowing in this case,
which is collateral not flowing. And
this is what a higher SOFR rate would
mean and what the money market is
currently hedging in huge amounts
against. And that goes with other signs
of money problems, the dollar shock that
I've been telling you about, which shows
up in offshore parts of the world beyond
India's biggest junk bond borrower.
So, this private credit story, and
indeed 2008 itself, it's not about
specific firms. Now, those specific
firms, when they failed in 2008, as I
said, they gave you a sign, a very
visible symptom that something big was
wrong. But we can have something go
wrong without failures. In this case,
shadow bank failures.
Now, the regulated banks like Deutsche
Bank, they're going to be part of this
because they're exposed, but this won't
be bringing any of the big ones down
like we saw 18 years ago. That's not
what we're talking about here. What we
are talking about is what turns off the
money and credit to the wider system.
Just as important, how long it might
stay turned off. And then what that
deflation unleashes in the real economy,
where it really counts, which is jobs
and incomes.
And as I told you in that webinar a
month ago, it's not about credit losses,
it gets to be about this mistrust. And
as we just went over, there is every
reason to see why everyone can see with
their plain eyes how things aren't
adding up. There are all the signs of a
credit cycle downturn, and what looks to
be a big one given the garbage bubble
which preceded it. And how far that
goes, how big it gets, will depend on
several factors including money flow.
And the more that amplifies the negative
results, the greater the chance not just
of a credit crunch wrecking things in
the real economy and the markets in the
short run or the intermediate term
really, but like 2008 leaving permanent
scars this time on the shadow banking
landscape, which would then deprive the
real economy of yet another recovery.
It's not Deutsche Bank becoming the next
Lehman Brothers that we need to worry
about cuz that's not really going to
happen anyway. It's the repeat of
another permanent crunch or what
economists like to call a unit root.
Though economists wrongly say unit roots
aren't possible. We've already seen
that's not true. That was 2008. So the
real downside here is not repeating
2008, it's repeating the aftermath.
My webinar for March is still available
here on the channel. In fact, that's the
one I got linked below. I'll even make
the deal, the webinar deal for Euro
Dollar University subscriptions. I'll
turn that one back on again if you're
interested. But I highly recommend you
check that out and to everyone else,
thank you very much for joining me. Huge
thanks to Euro Dollar University members
and subscribers and until next time,
take care.